Finding Aid for Karl J. Belser Papers, 1924-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Karl J. Belser Papers 1924-1972
Belser, Karl J. (Karl Jacob), 1902-1972.
1 oversize folders
4.4 linear feet
85737 Aa 2;UAm
Urban planning specialist. Reports, sketches, and other material relating to the development of the Willow Run Bomber Plant area in Wayne County, Michigan, during World War II; studies of the proposed Detroit Civic Center, 1952; also papers concerning his later work as planning director in Santa Clara County, California; letter from Frank Lloyd Wright; and sketchbooks with drawings and watercolors of buildings and scenes in Europe, the United States, and Taiwan; also photographs of Belser.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Karl J. Belser (donor no. 5483 ) and came to the library in 1974-1975 with a small addition in 1983.
The collection is open to research.
Subjects:
Belser, Karl J. (Karl Jacob), 1902-1972.; City planning--California--Santa Clara County.; City planning--Michigan--Wayne County.; Civic Center (Detroit, Mich.); Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Santa Clara County (Calif.); Wayne County (Mich.); Willow Run Bomber Plant.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Belser, Karl J. (Karl Jacob), 1902-1972.; Buildings.; Europe.; Taiwan.; Grand Canyon (Ariz.)
Contributors:
Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Paintings.; Photographs.
- Topical files
  - Agriculture planning 1954-1966, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - A.I.P. skit (Box 1)
  - Belser, Karl
    - Personal (awards, clippings, humor, etc.) (Box 1)
    - Boston memorabilia 1927-1928 (Box 1)
    - Thoughts on religion (Box 1)
    - Memorial service (and condolences) 1972 (Box 1)
    - Sheetz family (KJB's mother) (Box 1)
  - California Planning Commissioners handbook 1954 (Box 1)
  - California, University of: Speech re Santa Clara Valley 1970 (Box 1)
  - City Planning courses, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1953-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Detroit (general studies) (Box 1)
  - Detroit Civic Center Study, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Greenbelt studies (Box 1)
  - Hexagonal pattern studies (Box 1)
  - Industrial Development (Box 1)
  - Krushkhov, Abraam (Box 1)
  - Lambda-Alpha 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Laney College lecture 1971 (Box 1)
  - Los Angeles (urban redevelopment) 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Montalvo Association 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Natural Beauty (Box 2)
  - Open Space, Committee on, Reports 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Parks and Recreation Planning, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Pittsburgh Glass: Small House Award (Box 2)
  - Quest Club Speeches, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Radford talk 1933 "The Development of American Architecture" (Box 2)
  - Rapid Transit (Box 2)
  - Redevelopment Sketches, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Regional Development, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - San Diego (Box 3)
  - Speech 1969 "The Land Crisis" (Box 3)
  - San Jose (Box 3)
  - Santa Cruz (Box 3)
  - Santa Rosa. Report 1969 re open space (Box 3)
  - Stein, Clarence (Box 3)
  - Subdivision Problems (Box 3)
  - Taiwan (Box 3)
  - Teacher's Day 1970 (Box 3)
  - Unitarian Church miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Willow Run bomber Plant (Box 3)
  - Wright, Frank Lloyd (Box 3)
  - Zion Lutheran Church, Ann Arbor (Box 3)
  - Zoning, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Published
  - Printed material (Box 3)
  - Printed material (cont.) (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook 1969-1972 (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Sketchbooks
    - France 1929-1936, Pencil, watercolor, and ink (Box 5)
      (some drawings done while on the Booth Traveling Fellowship)
      (sketchbook no. 1)
    - United States, including Grand Canyon 1926-1931, Pencil, colored pencil, and pencil and ink (Box 5)
      (sketchbook no. 2)
    - England 1929, 1937 (1), Pencil with one in chalk (Box 5)
      (sketchbook no. 3)
    - Italy, Germany, Scotland, Scandinavia, Switzerland 1925-1937, Pencil with one in ink (Box 5)
      (sketchbook no. 4)
    - Taiwan 1968 "Taiwan Notes, Karl J. Belser" with printed contents table, Reproduction of Crayon and Wash (Box 5)
      (sketchbook no. 5)